A Guide to the Papers of Virginius Dabney,
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Virginius Dabney 1902-1983
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-ag
This collection consists of 9 boxes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired as a gift on 21 June 1983.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Virginius Dabney contain extensive correspondence carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, African Americans, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, will, & clippings re death of Lily Dabney, 1946, 1967, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, news releases, and editorials re Dabney's receipt of Sigma Delta Chi Distinguished Service Award, 1948 Feb-1949 May (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re Richard Heath Dabney Scholarship at the University of Virginia, 1964 Dec.-1970 Oct. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and notes re Guggenheim Fellowship, 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re speaking engagements, 1969 April-1979 Apr., n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and notes re nomination of Dumas Malone for Pulitzer Prize, 1972 Jan. -1974 Aug. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, speeches, and clippings re Dabney's receipt of Thomas Jefferson Award for Public Service, 1972 May-1973 Feb. (Box 1)
  - Letters re Save Capitol Square Committee, 1974 Jan. -Feb. (Box 1)
  - Richard M. Nixon to Virginius Dabney, 1981 July 6, 16; w/envelope and TLS (carbon), Dabney to Nixon. ALS. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, brochures, and clippings re U.S. Bicentennial Society, 1974-1979, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Letters and newspaper clippings re The Patriots, U.S. Bicentennial Society publication, 1975 Oct. -1976 Apr., n.d. (Box 1)
- Across the Years
  - Across the Years, n.d.; TMs (electrostatic copy) w/autograph corrections. 2 folders. (Box 1)
  - Across the Years, n.d.; TMs (electrostatic copy) w/autograph corrections. 2 folders. (Box 2)
- The Face of Virginia: A Pictorial Study
  - Correspondence and notes re The Face of Virginia, 1949 Jan., 1962 Jul.-1964 Mar., n.d. (Box 2)
  - The Face of Virginia, n.d.; TMss (original and electrostatic copy) w/autograph corrections (Box 2)
  - The Face of Virginia, n.d.; Galley proofs (Box 2)
  - Reviews of The Face of Virginia, 1963 Nov. (Box 2)
- The Jefferson Scandals
  - Correspondence re The Jefferson Scandals, 1979 Dec. -1980 Jan., n.d. (Box 2)
  - Letters to Dabney re The Jefferson Scandals, 1981 Jun. -1983 Feb., n.d. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, clippings, and notes re Sally Hemings, by Barbara Chase-Riboud, 1979 Jan. -1980 Jun., n.d. (Box 2)
  - Notes and documents re Thomas Jefferson and Sally Hemings, 1954, 1975-1981, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Notes re Jefferson: An Intimate Biography, by Fawn Brodie, 1980, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Early drafts of The Jefferson Scandals, incomplete, TMss (original and electrostatic copies) w/autograph corrections (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Reviews of The Jefferson Scandals, 1981 May-1982 Apr., n.d. (Box 3)
- Mr. Jefferson's University
  - Correspondence w/Frank Hereford, Jr., Walker Cowen, and Alexander Gilliam re Mr. Jefferson's University, 1976 Oct. -1981 Oct. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence w/Charles E. Moran, Jr., re Mr. Jefferson's University, 1977 Jun. -1980 May, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and notes re foreword and appendix of Mr. Jefferson's University, 1980 Jan., n.d. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence w/University Press of Virginia re Mr. Jefferson's University, 1980 Dec. -1983 Mar., n.d. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re Mr. Jefferson's University, 1981 Sept. -1983 May, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Notes for Mr. Jefferson's University: 1920-1930, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Notes for Mr. Jefferson's University: 1930-1940, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Notes for Mr. Jefferson's University: 1931-1940, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Notes for Mr. Jefferson's University: 1941-1947, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Notes for Mr. Jefferson's University: 1947-1959, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Notes for Mr. Jefferson's University: 1947-1959 (cont'd.), n.d. (Box 5)
  - Notes for Mr. Jefferson's University: 1949-1959, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Notes re Mr. Jefferson's University: 1959-1974, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Notes for Mr. Jefferson's University: 1959-1974, 1973-1980, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Notes for Mr. Jefferson's University: 1968-1972, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous notes re Mr. Jefferson's University:, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Mr. Jefferson's University:, n.d.; TMs (electrostatic copy), w/autograph corrections. (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Reviews of Mr. Jefferson's University:, 1981 Sept. -1983 Mar. (Box 6)
  - Financial statements re Mr. Jefferson's University:, 1978 Mar. -1980 May (Box 6)
- Editorials
  - Editorials by Dabney re state hours law for working women, 1937 Aug. -1938 June (Box 6)
  - Editorials by Dabney re Hitler's seizure of Austria and the Czechoslovak crisis, 1938 Mar. -Oct. (Box 6)
  - Editorials by Dabney re the European war and the role of America, 1939 Aug. -Sept. (Box 6)
  - Editorials by Dabney re state electoral frauds, 1945 Aug. -Oct. (Box 7)
  - Editorials by Dabney, 1930-1959, 1960-1981, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Editorials by Dabney re Europe, Mexico and Canada, 1954-1967 (Box 7)
- Speeches and Articles
  - "America's Bicentennial '76 College: The Story of Hampden-Sydney College in Virginia." by Dabney, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, clippings, and notes re "Did It All Begin In Massachusetts?" and the 350th Jamestown Festival, 1955 May-1957 Jul., n.d. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, notes, manuscripts, and clippings re "The GOP's Upsurge in Dixie," by Dabney, 1962-1963, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, notes, and clippings re "The Pace Is Important," by Dabney, 1963-1965 (Box 7)
  - "Richard Heath Dabney --A Memoir," by Dabney, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Speeches and articles by Dabney, 1952-1964, 1965, 1967-1973, 1976, n.d.; (7 folders) (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Citations presented to Dabney, 1945-1971 (Box 8)
  - Obituaries for Richard Heath Dabney, 1947 May 17 (Box 8)
  - Programs of events at which Dabney was a speaker, 1972-1983 (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Photographs of Virginius Dabney, 1902-1977, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Photographs of Dabney family members, 1914-1965, n.d. (Box 9)
- Printed Material
  - The Monthly Chronicle, 1922 Feb-May (Box 9)
  - The Myth of the Ride of Paul Revere, 1927 (Box 9)
  - "Medicine in a Changing World," by Dabney, Bulletin, Medical College of Virginia, 1939 Feb. 1 (Box 9)
  - Newspaper and magazine articles re Dabney, 1958-1983 (Box 9)
  - Photograph of Episcopal High School Baseball Team, 1917 (Box 9)
  - Photograph of Delta Kappa Epsilon (University of Virginia), 1917-1918 (Box 9)
  - Photograph of T.I.L.K.A., 1918-1919 (Box 9)
  - Photograph of Delta Kappa Epsilon (University of Virginia), 1918-1919 (Box 9)
  - Photograph of Delta Kappa Epsilon (University of Virginia), 1920-1921 (Box 9)
  - 2 photographs of Dabney receiving honorary degree at University of Richmond, 1940 Apr. 19 (Box 9)
  - Certificate appointing Dabney Civilian Aide to the Secretary of the Army for the State of Virginia, 1947 Dec. 3 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence re University of Virginia history, 1976 Nov. -1980 Jan., 1980 Feb.-1982 Nov., n.d.; Restricted material (Box 9)